A Guide to the New Jersey Zinc Corporation [Austinville, Virginia] Records, 1850-1969
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
New Jersey Zinc Corporation [Austinville, VA] Records, 1850-1969
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1991-032
55 cu. ft. 58 boxes; 3 oversize folders
The collection consists of maps, blueprints, and files of the New Jersey Zinc Corporation operations in Austinville, Virgina.
New Jersey Zinc Corporation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The New Jersey Zinc Corporation [Austinville, Virginia] Records were donated to Special Collections in 1991.
Alternate Form Available
...
Historical Note
The lead mines of southwest Virginia were first discovered by Colonel John Chiswell in 1756. Chiswell mined lead ore on the New River in Augusta County (now Wythe County) from 1760 to 1766, and furnished large supplies of lead to Virginia during the French and Indian War. A fort and trading post were sut up at this time near the mines. Chiswell died in 1766, and ownership of the mines was trasnferred to William Byrd. The mines were leased to the state during the Revolutionary War.
In 1789 Moses and Stephen Austin contacted for the lead mines and bought them from the Commonwealth of Virginia. Due to mismanagement, the lead mines reverted back to the state in 1802. In 1806, Thomas Jackson bought the proerty, now in the town of Austinville, in Wythe County, at a public auction in Richmond. He constructed a shot-tower on the New River, which operated from 1812 to 1830 and still stands today.
From 1830 to 1898, the property was mined by Daniel Sheffey and David Pierce or their descendants. From 1838 to the 1850s, the firm was called the Wythe Lead Mines Company. The Union Lead Mine Company, as it was called in 1860, contributed more than 2,000 tons of lead to Confederate troops in the Civil War. After the discovery of zinc in the 1860s, the Union Lead Company formed the Wythe Lead and Zinc Company.
The Wythe Lead and Zinc Company sold all of its ore in 1898 to the Bertha Mineral Company, which operated in Pulaski, six miles northeast of Austinville. In 1902, the New Jersey Zinc Corporation purchased Bertha holdings and the Austinville property.
For more information on the early history of the Austinville lead and zinc mines, see: Austin, Vera Lee. 1977. The Southwest Virginia Lead Works, 1756-1802. Thesis (M.A.)--Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, 1977.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of maps, blueprints, and files of the New Jersey Zinc Corporation operations in Austinville, Virgina. Maps in the collection, dating from the 1930s-1960s, describe the geological plans, the Ivan hoe mines, hydrology, ore reserves, and geochemistry of the area, including portions of North Carolina. Eight rolls of blueprints depict equipment and furnace works.
Files include superintendent memos, tenant applications, Ivanhoe property records, employment records and correspondence, senoirity lists, unemployment compensation forms, contracts, deeds, death claims, and company rules and regulations. The collection also has some information on the Ivanhoe Furnace Company (1911-1913).
In addition, there are 31 volumes (1888-1908) of published materials: American Society of Mechanical Engineers. 1880. Transactions of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers. New York City: The Society.
Please note: This collection is unprocessed and the "Contents List" below is a preliminary inventory only.
Arrangement
Please note: This collection is unprocessed and the "Contents List" below is a preliminary inventory only. The collection is in its original order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
An additional accession relating to the New Jersey Zinc Corporation was donated to Special Collection in 1999. These materials are available as New Jersey Zinc Corporation (Austinville, VA) Records II, Ms2011-037.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South
Corporate Names:
Bertha Mineral Company.; New Jersey Zinc Corporation.; Union Lead Mining Company. (Austinville, Va.); Wythe Lead and Zinc Mine Company.
Contents List
- Reports and files. (Box 1)
  Scope and Content
  Personnel Dept. reports, montly and annual (c. 1949-1969) -Applications for employment (c. June 1920-April 1923) -Austinville property -1965 VICC Company property -Chaffin: folders dated 1951-1958 -Chaffin: illustration -Chaffin: outstanding interests -Chaffin estate
- Correspondence and files. (Box 2)
  Business correspondence and legal documents -Wythe and Carroll County properties -Carter lands -Middletown and Frederick County materials -Timbervill -Options agreements: Georgia pyrite area -North Carolina -Stafford County -Bertha mines -Stoots-Trepass suit -Chaffin
- Correspondence and files. (Box 3)
  Rent statements for Bertha Mineral Company (12/1913-12/1939) -Business correspondence
- Publications. (Box 4)
  American Society of Mechanical Engineers. 1880. Transactions of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers. New York City: The Society.
- Maps, charts, and files. (Box 5)
  Plot plans: Austinville Elementary School. Wytheville, Va (May 1950) -Topographical maps -Lab analysis: Speedwell, Sugar Grove -Charts of grand geophysics area, Callahan Mining Corp, Louisa County, Va
- Correspondence, deeds, and files. (Box 6)
  Business correspondence and land surveys -C.T. & Mary Graham -Sanders Mine -Ivanhoe ready deeds -Pulaski, Delton, and Barren Spring, Virginia -Thurston Tract, Pulaski -Nissen Mine -Swansea Land and Improvement Company -Pulaski and Osborne areas, Russell County, Va -Porter Bank and Bearer Creek near Saltwell areas, Smyth County, Va -Lease, Marion office -Poplar Camp, Patterson area
- Reports and files. (Box 7)
  Minor accident reports (c.1940s) -Bulletin board notices -Real estate (c.1950s-1960s)
- Publications. (Box 8)
- Correspondence, files, and publications. (Box 9)
  Correspondence regarding union issues; officers and commmittee members -Recreation 1/4/1950 - American Society of Mechanical Engineers. 1880. Transactions of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers. New York City: The Society.
- Files. (Box 10)
  Rent statements (c.Jan 1940-Dec 1944) -Recreation (c.1926-1958) -Exploration department: payroll changes, requests for forms, exams, compensation -Documents regarding garnishments, arbitration, grievances, pay practices, and union matters
- Publications. (Box 11)
- Drawings, reports, and files. (Box 12)
  Possible index to maps and drawings -Ivanhoe headframe steel drawings -Accident reports (Jan 1926-Dec 1926) -Residential inspections -Property rights and holdings of NJ Zinc (1958?) -Geochemical results for Northeast Hill Belt, Smyth and Bland Counties, Va
- Files? (Box 13)
  No inventory
- Files, correspondence, and maps. (Box 14)
  Personnel records, including work program -Embree Slimes -Correspondence, insurance agreements, purchase agreements -Sanders Mine/property -Carter Jackson files -Maps -W. M. Cornett estate -Patterson area, Va -Introduction cards -Labor/union agreements -Group picture: White House reception (10/4/1929) -Lease agreements, including Ivanhoe Mining & Smelting Company, others -Maps and plats
- Photographs and maps. (Box 15)
  Group picture: N&W Railway Systems Efficienty Meeting, Bluefield, WV (October 22-23, 1929) -Group pictures: Association of Railway Claim Agents -Geologic maps for part of Virginia
- Geological surveys, charts, and technical documents. (Box 16-22)
  Geological surveys of the United States for various counties -Maps -Charts -Technical documents
- Files and correspondence. (Box 23)
  "Adventure to Baltimore," list of lead buyers, 1850 -Wythe Lead and Zinc Mine Company, capital stock certificates, 1889-1893 -Copies and transcripts of historical documents and data, 1901-1948 -Recreation, 1912-1915, 1916-1918 -Schools and churches, 1913-1919, 1921-1926 -Applications for employment, including correspondence, 1914-1915 -Employment applications, 1916-1919 -State tax returns, 1916-1935 -Recreation and zinc publications, 1941-1943 -Tax returns, 1936-1969 -Recreation and trade publications, 1944-1946, 1947-1949 -College recruitment program, 1951-1952 -Applications - salary (rejected), 1952 -Labor Policy and Practice: Bulletin to Management, 1952-1953 -Wage surveys, 1952 -Employment records, including correspondence, 1952-1959
- Files and correspondence. (Box 24)
  Monthly payroll, accident and compensation reports, 1917-1928, 1929-1948 -Market development division, 1944-1949, 1950-1954 -Property sales, 1952-1959 --Labor Policy and Practice: Bulletin to Management, 1953-1954 -Wage surveys, 1955-1956, 1957-1959 -Employment correspondence, 1920 -Report and analysis of financial condition and productivity of Wythe Lead and Zinc Company, 1883 -Lead mine history, 1917 -"The Story of Austinville," by W. O. Borchedt, 1950 -Lot sales, Little Mountain subdivision, 1931-1941 -"The Story of the New Jersey Zinc Company," by G. B. Hechel, 1934
- Maps and blueprints
  - Maps and blueprints, 1930s-1960s, n.d. (Folder 1)
  - Map of Property from Austinville East Below Ivanhoe towards Pierce's Mill (photocopy), c. 1930 (Folder 1)
  - Geological, railroad, and mining maps (Box 25)
  - Architectural plans, Bertha Division, c. 1947 (Box 26)
  - Bertha Mineral Co., North and South Section through "Shot Shaft", Austinville (Box 27)
  - Key maps showing Austinville surface and plane table sheet co. (Box 27)
  - Austinville area surface maps, 1949-10 (Box 27)
  - US Dept. of Interior, Bureau of Mine, Proj. 15-165, Idol-Dalton Zn. Prospect, Grainger County, Tennessee (Box 27)
  - Mining maps (Box 28)
  - Mining maps, North Carolina, 1967-1970 (Box 29)
  - Ivanhoe and Austinville mining maps (Box 30)
  - Bertha statistics and contour maps, 1977-1980 (Box 31)
  - North Carolina, Delft mine area, 1967-1980 (Box 32)
  - Contour maps for New Jersey Zinc Corportation, 1956 (Box 33)
  - Ringwood area, Halifax County, North Carolina (Box 34)
  - Map showing Bertha Mineral Company's lands in Carroll County, Virginia, HGB-1, 1913 (Box 34)
  - Mechanical drawings (Box 35)
  - Austinville and Ivanhoe mining maps and water surveys, 1962 (Box 36)
  - Austinville, Ivanhoe geological maps, Simmerman Development Plan (Box 37)
  - Office building and plant, 1948-1975 (Box 38)
  - Black Lick, Speedwell, Fort Chiswell, Lead Mines Districts maps and Austinville office building (Box 39)
  - Oxide Furnace Drawings, Austinville, Virginia, 1920 (Box 40)
  - Geologic, topographic, and geochemistry maps for southwestern Virginia and western West Virginia, c. 1960s (Box 41)
  - Maps of southwestern Virginia (Box 42)
  - Contour maps, longitudinal sections, stratigraphic sections, aerial photo (Box 43)
  - Geological and topographical maps, southwestern Virginia, c. 1940s-1960s (Box 44)
  - Callahan Mining Corporation sections, New Jersey Zinc maps and sections, c. 1970s (Box 45)
  - Cofer Mine, Julia Mine, Mineral, Virginia, c. 1960s-1970s (Box 46)
  - Geological maps of East Tennessee, State of Tennessee, Department of Conservation, Division of Geology, compiled by John Rodgers, 1952 (Box 48)
  - Stope sections of Ivanhoe, Virginia, New Jersey Zinc (Box 48)
  - Geological and contour maps of North Carolina, South Carolina, and Virginia (Box 49)